Finding Aid for Original Dulcimer Players Club
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Original Dulcimer Players Club records 1963-2012
Original Dulcimer Players Club
0.5 linear feet and 1 box of audiotapes
8533 Bp 2
Organization dedicated to furthering "the art of playing the Hammered Dulcimer" founded in 1963 by Elgia C. Hickok in Michigan. Records include correspondence, minutes, newsletters, programs, event flyers, and oral histories, sound recordings of interviews and meetings, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Original Dulcimer Players Club in (donor no. 6491 ) in several accessions in the 1980s, and by Paul Gifford (donor no. 7128 ) in November 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Original Dulcimer Players Club (ODPC) was founded in 1963 by Elgia C. Hickok in Michigan. The group aims to "promote and preserve the art of playing the Hammered Dulcimer." Beginning in 1974, the ODPC has hosted a FunFest each summer at the Osceola County Fairgrounds in Evart, Michigan. The event includes concerts, workshops, and informal jam sessions. The event focuses on the hammered dulcimer, but other instruments are welcome as well (excluding band brass instruments, woodwind instruments with mechanical keys, most drums, and electrified instruments).
The Original Dulcimer Players Club records document the group's organization and activities from its founding in 1963. The records are arranged into six series: Administrative materials, Publications and events, Articles and newspaper clippings, Miscellaneous, Visual materials, and Audio materials.
Subjects:
Dulcimer.; Music--Michigan.; Musicians--Michigan.; Original Dulcimer Players Club.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Evart (Mich.); Fair Lane (Dearborn, Mich.); Music ensembles.; Ruffwater Stringband.; Stringed instruments.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Cox, Eugene.; Cox, Viola.; Hickok, Mildred.
Contributors:
Cox, Eugene.; Cox, Viola.; Hickok, Mildred.
Genre Terms:
Interviews.; Microfilms.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
- Administrative materials, 1972-1983
  The Administrative materials series consists of governing documents, correspondence, minutes, and other materials.
  - By-laws, 1979 and financial document, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, and other materials, 1973-1983 (Box 1)
- Publications and events, 1971-2012
  The Publications and events series includes organization newsletters, FunFest programs, event flyers, and a calendar.
  - Newsletters, 1984-1997 and 2012, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Funfest programs, 1994-1997, 2000 and 2012 (Box 1)
  - Flyers, 1971-1989 (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
- Articles and newspaper clippings, 1965-1984
  The Articles and newspaper clippings series is composed of various news articles about the ODPC and dulcimer playing. Most clippings originate from the Grand Rapids Press. Issues of the Evart Review are also included as well as one issue of North Country Folk.
  - Newspaper articles, 1965-1973 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles, 1967-1984 (Box 1)
  - North Country Folk article, 1981 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous, 1976-1986
  The Miscellaneous series includes two essays or papers, materials related to the oral history project, and other mixed materials. These mixed materials may overlap with the series above.
  - "Michigan's Hammered Dulcimers" by Jan Alm, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Materials regarding "It's not a bagpipe" essay, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Oral history project, 1978 and 1986 (Box 1)
  - Mixed materials including oral history project materials, correspondence, news articles, and event materials, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
- Visual materials, 1974-1998
  The Visual materials series consists of photographs of ODPC people and events, as well as a reel of microfilm with ODCP scrapbook.
  - Photographs of meetings and performances, 1970s (Box 1)
  - Photographs of dulcimer players and events, 1974-1998 (Box 1)
  - Photograph of the Ruffwater Stringband, September 12, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (on microfilm reel) (Box 2)
- Audio materials, 1963-1980
  - Meetings
    The Audio materials series contains audiotapes of ODPC meetings and oral history interviews.
    - First meeting of the Original Dulcimer Players Club, Barryton, MI, September 28, 1963 (Box 2)
    - "Dulcimers at Barryton" (Box 2)
      (probably meeting in 1964)
    - ODPC meeting, September 30, 1967 (Box 2)
    - ODPC meeting, May 1968 (Box 2)
    - ODPC meeting, September 27, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Oral History Project
    - Viola Cox, ODPC Oral History Project Tape 1, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Mildred Hickok, ODPC Oral History Project Tape 2, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Eugene Cox, ODPC Oral History Project Tape 3, 1980 (Box 2)